Guide to University of Chicago Library Exhibit Publications Collection 1964-2009
University of Chicago Library
- Research at the Center: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of Special Collections, Research has been at the center of Special Collections at the University of Chicago from its formative years. Just as the University itself has been defined by consistent emphasis on the production and dissemination of knowledge, the Library's rare books, manuscripts, and archives have always been collected and valued for their scholarly and educational potential. The past decade has brought many new ways of stimulating and supporting teaching and scholarship at the University. In celebration of the 50th anniversary of the 1953 founding of Special Collections, "Research at the Center" presents a portrait of the way we work now to preserve and provide broadened access to primary sources across a range of disciplines and formats. Special Collections Research Center September 1, 2003 – January 31, 2004
- Dr. Bernard Fantus: Father of the Blood Bank; and Researching Chicago Medical History: Sources in the University of Chicago Library, In 1937, Dr. Bernard Fantus (1874-1940) established what is now recognized as the world's first blood bank when he opened a blood preservation laboratory at Chicago's Cook County Hospital. Drawing on a recent gift of historical materials from Fantus's niece, Muriel Fulton, this exhibition will examine the creation of the blood bank and other significant achievements of a pioneering medical researcher and physician. For over a century and a half, the history of medicine in the city of Chicago has been shaped by significant contributions to research and innovations in clinical care. "Research Chicago Medical History" highlights some of the most important archival source materials on Chicago medicine in the Special Collections Research Center, including selections from the medical manuscript collections originally acquired by the John Crerar Library. Materials on display will include physicians' letters, journals, medical school lecture notes, publications, historic photographs, and medals and other awards. Special Collections Research Center November 1, 2004 – February 1, 2005
- Life of the Spirit, Life of the Mind: Rockefeller Memorial Chapel at 75, As the spirit of religion should penetrate and control the University, so that building which represents religion ought to be the central and dominant feature of the University group." This bold mission is etched in stone at the entrance of Rockefeller Memorial Chapel. Drawing on photographs and documents from the University Archives, this exhibition explores how the planners of Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, Chapel Deans, the student body, and the broader community have interpreted this mission to shape the architecture of the Chapel as well as the programs it supports. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 2004 – June 1, 2004
- From Poetry to Verse: The Making of Modern Poetry, Drawing upon the archives of Poetry, Chicago Review, Big Table, Verse, LVNG, and the papers of The Poetry Center of Chicago, the exhibit tracks the evolution and changing character of poetry from 1912 to the present. This includes a study of how the publishing process impacts upon the creative process and may help define the meaning of modern poetry at specific times. It will also permit an inquiry into the establishment of literary reputations. Special Collections Research Center September 1, 2005 – February 28, 2006
- Printing for the Modern Age: Commerce, Craft, and Culture in the RR Donnelley ArchivePrinting for the Modern Age: Commerce, Craft, and Culture in the RR Donnelley Archive, Printing for the Modern Age: Commerce, Craft, and Culture in the RR Donnelley Archive" explores the enormous impact that printing technology and print media have had on modern life. Materials in the exhibition are drawn from the RR Donnelley Archive, the historic corporate archive of R.R. Donnelley and Sons Company, the Chicago-based firm that has become the largest provider of print and print-related products and services in the world. Special Collections Research Center September 1, 2006 – February 28, 2007
- Images of Prayer, Politics and Everyday Life from the Harry and Branks Sondheim Jewish Heritage Collection, The exhibition marks the gift of the Harry and Branka Sondheim Collection to the University of Chicago Library. The Sondheim collection provides a rich, varied, and detailed vision of Jewish life from the sixteenth to the twentieth century. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 2008 – July 31, 2008
- On Equal Terms: Educating Women at the University of Chicago, The University of Chicago's original articles of incorporation, crafted in 1892, state that the institution will "provide, impart, and furnish opportunities for all departments of higher education to persons of both sexes on equal terms," thus writing coeducation into the University's founding principles. Yet integrating the sexes into the curriculum, research agenda, and extracurricular life proved to be a difficult and as yet unfinished task. The history of women at the University of Chicago is uneven, full of successes and failures that reflect both Chicago's unique intellectual community and larger trends in academia. Special Collections Research Center March 1, 2009 – July 31, 2009